Guide to the Administrative Records of George D. Stoddard MC 90
New York University Archives
Administrative Records of George D. Stoddard
Bulk, 1953-1964
1941-1967
MC 90
New York University Archives
0.25 linear feet
This collection comprises documents that arose from Stoddard's affiliation with New York University. This collection will be of use to researchers interested in education reform and curriculum development and the recent history of NYU. There are a few items of particular note, such as draft copies of Stoddard's proposal for the Gallatin School and the University's Self Study, which Stoddard directed. Copies of Stoddard's Dual Progress Plan are included, along with a large volume of correspondence, notes, and literature relating to it. Also included is Stoddard's 1963 Mission of New York University, which was presented to the Ford Foundation as well as the text of a speech he delivered at NYU's 124th commencement ceremonies in 1956.
Biography of George D. Stoddard
Born in 1897 in Carbondale, Pennsylvania, George D. Stoddard was active in UNESCO, served on the board of the Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, and was the author of many books on children and education. Stoddard's affiliation with New York University began in 1953 when he was named Chairman of the Directing Committee of the University's $250,000 Self Study. Before this appointment, Stoddard had been President of the University of Illinois for seven years, Commissioner of Education of the State of New York, President of the University of the State of New York, and Dean of the University of Iowa Graduate School, from which he had received his Ph.D.
In 1956 Stoddard was named Chancellor and Executive Vice President responsible for the educational policy and administration of New York University's schools, colleges, and divisions and also served as Chief Executive Officer in the president's absence. Stoddard retired from this position in 1964, beginning a three-year term as a distinguished professor of education. He later left NYU to become Vice Chancellor of Long Island University. Stoddard left university administration when he retired in 1969 as Chancellor of Long Island University.
Scope and Contents
The documents in this collection deal only with Stoddard's years dealing with New York University, including those in which he served as director of the NYU Self Study. Included in this collection is information dealing with Stoddard's administrative affairs at NYU; programs from various ceremonies; letters detailing of Stoddard's own appointments as well as those of others; annual reports that he made as dean of the School of Education; information about the Dual Progress Plan, an education system he created; clippings from various newspapers and magazines about Stoddard; letters of congratulation that he received over the years; and information dealing with the creation of the Gallatin division. Also included in the collection is the mission of New York University as submitted to the Ford Foundation, press releases and information about NYU's Self Study. There are some contact sheets included in this collection that have to do with the Dual Progress Plan. The material in the collection spans from 1941 to 1974, with the bulk falling between 1953 and 1964.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically in a single series, filling two boxes.
Access
This collection is open without restrictions.
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President (David D. Henry and Carroll V. Newsom, John E. Ivey, Jr., George D. Stoddard, and Russell D. Niles) - RG 6.0
Administrative Files of the Dean of the School of Education, Daniel E. Griffiths - RG 26.0.1
Armsey, James; Dodson, Dan W., (Dan William), 1907-1995; Ford Foundation.; Harvard University. Graduate School of Education.; Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; Hester, James M., 1924-; Katsh, Abraham Isaac, 1908-; New York University. Gallatin Division.; New York University. School of Education.; Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-1981; Willits, Joseph H. (Joseph Henry), 1889-
- Administrative Records of George D. Stoddard
  - Administrative Affairs, 1955 - 1964, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports: Dean, School of Education (1957-58), 1957 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointments, 1954 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ceremonies: Programs and Speeches, 1956 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Congratulations, 1941-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dual Progress Plan, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gallatin Division Proposals, 1961 - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mission of New York University (Draft) Presented to Ford Foundation, 1962 - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Press Clippings - NYU Publications, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Press Clippings - Metropolitan Publications, 1953 - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Press Clippings - Other Publications, 1953 - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases, 1953 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Self-Study, 1955 - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)